Guide to the Cochrane Family Papers, 1777-1957 and undated bulk 1850-1905 RL.00239
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cochrane Family papers
1777-1957 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cochrane family
RL.00239
5.5 Linear Feet
Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane served in the British Navy from 1839-1886, where he fought in the Anglo-Chinese war and rose to the rank of admiral. He was also instrumental in administering the Trinidad Lake Asphalt Company during its early years. His brother, Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane was also active in the Royal Navy from 1847-1873, participating in the British campaign to suppress the slave trade in West Africa during the 1860s. He was also a landowner and landlord of the Redcastle Estate in County Donegal, Ireland, and served in his later years as High Sheriff for County Donegal. The collection contains correspondence, legal and financial documents, notes and writings, notebooks and diaries, clippings, printed books and pamphlets, photographs, maps, charts, diagrams and technical drawings pertaining to the lives and careers of Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro and Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane, and to the Trinidad Lake Asphalt Company. The papers span the years 1777-1957, with the bulk of the collection being dated from 1850-1905, and document the naval careers of Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane and Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane, the role of the Cochrane family as landlords in Western Ulster, and the development of the colonial asphalt industry in Trinidad during the 19th century.
4125 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Cochrane Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1985-1988.
Biographical Note
Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald
1775 Dec. 14 Born to Archibald Cochrane, 9th Earl of Dundonald, and Anne (Gilchrist) Cochrane
1793 Joined crew of H.M.S. Hind, of which his uncle, Sir Alexander Cochrane, was then captain
1796 Appointed lieutenant
1796-1798 Served on the North American station
1798-1800 Served on the French and Spanish coasts during the early years of the Napoleonic wars
1800-1801 Commander of H.M.S. Speedy
1801 Made captain Captured by a French squadron and exchanged
1802-1803 Studied at Edinburgh University
1805 Cruised off the Azores
1806 Cruised in the Bay of Biscay Failed bid at the House of Commons for Honiton
1807 Entered Parliament as a Whig for the constituency of Westminster
1808-1809 Cruised the French and Spanish coasts
1812 Aug. 8 Married Katherine Corbett Frances Barnes ( Kitty Barnes) in secret at Annan, County Dumfries
1813 Appointed flag-captain to his uncle, Sir Alexander Cochrane
1814 Tried for stock-market fraud and conspiracy Expelled from Royal Navy, Parliament, and Order of the Bath
1814-1816 Paid fines through penny subscriptions
1817 Accepted command of the Chilean navy
1818 June 22 Publicly married Katherine Corbett Frances Barnes, daughter of Thomas Barnes of Romford, Essex
1819-1822 Fought for independence for Chile and Peru against the Spanish forces
1823-1825 Fought for independence for Brazil as admiral of the Brazilian fleet
1827-1828 Admiral of the Greek navy
1831 Succeeded to Earldom after the death of Archibald Cochrane
1832 Reinstated in the British navy and promoted to rear-admiral
1847 Reinstated as Knight Grand Cross in Order of the Bath
1848 Returned to command at sea as Commander-in-Chief of the H.M.S. Wellesley
1848-1852 Served on the Wellesley in North America and the West Indies, where he surveyed Pitch Lake, Trinidad, and became involved in the early use of the lake as a source of asphalt
1851 Promoted to admiral
1860 Oct. 31 Died in London
Thomas Barnes Cochrane, 11th Earl of Dundonald
1814 Apr. 18 Born to Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald, and Katherine Corbett Frances Cochrane
1847 Dec. 1 Married Louisa Harriet Mackinnon
1885 Jan. 15 Died, succeeded by his son, Douglas Mackinnon Baillie Hamilton Cochrane, 12th Earl of Dundonald
Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane
1824 Sept. 24 Born to Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald, and Katherine Corbett Frances Cochrane
1839 Apr. Entered Royal Navy
1854 Promoted to rank of captain Participated in the capture of Bomarsund during the Crimean War
1855 Feb. 7-1856 May 12 Captain of H.M.S. Horatio, a guard ship at Sheerness
1856 May 14-1858 Sept. 8 Captain of H.M.S. Niger in the East Indies and China, where he served in the Anglo-Chinese war
1858 Sept. 8 Invalided
1869 Apr.-1870 May Superintendent of Sheerness dockyard
1870 Made rear-admiral
1873 June 6-1876 Apr. 15 Commander-in-Chief of the Pacific Squadron
1876 Made vice-admiral
1881 Promoted to admiral
1886 Retired from navy
1889 Knighted
1905 Aug. 20 Died
Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane
1834 June 4 Born to Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald, and Katherine Corbett Frances Cochrane
1847 Entered Royal Navy
1847-1855 Served on board the ships Victory, Hibernian, and Trafalgar
1854 Aug. 13 Participated in the capture of Bomarsund during the Crimean War aboard H.M.S. Wellesley
1854 Aug. 29 Made lieutenant of the Edinburgh
1856 Served as lieutenant-commander of H.M.S. Chub
1864 Sept. 15 Married Adelaide Blackwall, daughter of Samuel W. Blackwall, Governor of Sierra Leone
1864 Oct. 3 Death of wife Adelaide
1866 Oct. 16 Married Elizabeth Frances Maria Katherine Doherty, only child of Richard Doherty of Redcastle
1868 Apr. 16-1870 Apr. 7 Commander of H.M.S. Petrel off the Cape of Good Hope and West coast of Africa Participated in the suppression of the slave trade
1873 Retired as captain
1879 High Sheriff of County Donegal
1911 Feb. 2 Died at his Redcastle estate, Inishowen, County Donegal, Ireland
Collection Overview
The Cochrane Family Papers span the years 1777-1957, with the bulk of the papers being dated between 1850 and 1905. The collection consists of correspondence; legal and financial documents; personal, naval, and technical notes and other writings; notebooks, diaries, and almanacs; clippings and other saved print material; and photographs, maps, charts, drawings, diagrams, and other visual materials preserved by the Cochranes. The majority of these documents pertain to two members of the Cochrane family: the brothers Admiral Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane and Admiral Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane. The bulk of the papers deal with three principal subject areas: the naval careers of the brothers; family matters and finances, particularly the finances of their Redcastle Estate in County Donegal, Ireland; and business papers and correspondence relating to the family estates and the Trinidad Lake Asphalt Company, established by Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald, and continued by his son Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane. The collection is particularly rich in documenting the beginnings of the asphalt industry in Trinidad and land-use issues in Ireland during the 19th century. In addition, Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane was stationed off the coast of West Africa during much of the 1850s and 1860s, and the collection contains a number of documents relating to the British attempts during that time to suppress the African slave trade, an effort in which Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane was active. The collection is divided into three series, the Family Papers Series, the Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane Series, and the Trinidad Lake Asphalt Series, each of which are divided into subseries by format. This division retains the original division of the collection, but researchers should be aware that there is significant crossover between the subject areas of the Family Papers Series and the Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane Series, and those interested in one of these series should be aware that there may be pertinent material in the other.
The Family Papers Series, the largest of the three, documents two main subject areas: the naval careers of Ernest Grey Lambton and Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane, and the family finances relating to the Redcastle estate. The former of these is documented primarily in the Correspondence subseries and the Notes and Writings Subseries, while the latter is most heavily represented in the Legal and Financial Documents Subseries, which contains a number of rental and account books pertaining to the Cochrane and Doherty family estates in Ireland. The Cochranes were all active inventors, and the Legal and Financial Documents Subseries also includes patent forms for a number of inventions, including means of laying telegraph wire and ships' boilers and propulsion. The Notebooks and Diaries Subseries is comprised primarily of bound volumes of writings by Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane, documenting his daily activity and travels, although it does contain two notebooks used by Thomas Cochrane for surveying during his travels in the 1850s and an Irish Land Commission notebook belonging to Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane as well. The two remaining subseries, Print Materials and Visual Materials and Artifacts, are much smaller in size, and contain materials pertaining to both brothers, and to the family more generally.
The Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane Series contains material accessioned separately from the rest of the collection, which documents Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane's naval life and activities off the Western coast of Africa; his correspondence with Richard Doherty (whose daughter he later married) about financial and estate matters in County Donegal; and his time spent as a landlord in County Donegal, where he became High Sheriff and a member of the Grand Jury after retiring from the navy. The Correspondence Subseries contains Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane's correspondence with Samuel W. Blackwall of Sierra Leone; Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane; Thomas Barnes Cochrane; Richard Doherty; and others. Of the other subseries, the Legal and Financial Documents and Visual Materials subseries relate primarily to his life in County Donegal, while the Notebooks and Diaries and Notes and Writings subseries deal more extensively with his earlier naval career and time in West Africa. This series was kept separate from the Family Papers Series to preserve the original order of the documents. As should be clear from this description, however, many of the subject areas of this series overlap with those of the Family Papers Series, and researchers interested in the naval career of Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane or the Cochranes' role as landlords in Northern Ireland should also consult that series.
Finally, the Trinidad Lake Asphalt Series documents the Cochrane family's involvement in the early asphalt industry in Trinidad. The vast majority of the papers included here are those of Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane, who took over the job of overseeing the Cochrane properties and interests in Trinidad after he was invalided during the China wars. However, there are also materials of Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald, pertaining to the company. To be found here are business correspondence pertaining to the export of asphalt and bitumen from Trinidad, shipping arrangements, experiments conducted on the potential uses of bitumen from Pitch Lake, and other matters related to the establishment and operation of the business; notes relating to experiments conducted, and to the climate and area; legal documents establishing the company and documenting the extent of the Belle Vue, Mon Plaisir and Esperance Estates in Trinidad; maps and plans of these estates and of Pitch Lake; and two printed volumes and other miscellaneous items pertaining to Trinidad. The material contained in this series should be of interest to those researching the development and early stages of the asphalt industry, and to those interested in colonial business, finance, and resource use during the 19th century.
Clippings (information artifacts); Technical drawings; Account books; Maps; Admirals -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- History, Naval -- 19th century; Land use -- Ireland; Antislavery movements -- Great Britain -- History -- 19th century; Trinidad -- Commerce -- History; Donegal (Ireland: County) -- History; Watercolors (paintings); Asphalt industry -- History -- 19th century; Diaries; Nautical charts; Diagrams; Black-and-white photographs; Trinidad Lake Asphalt Company; Dundonald, Thomas Cochrane, Earl of, 1814-1885; Cochrane family; Cochran family; Cochrane, Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro, 1824-1905; Cochrane family; Dundonald, Thomas Cochrane, Earl of, 1775-1860; Cochrane, Ernest Grey Lambton, 1834-1911
- Family Papers Series, 1777-1930 and undated, bulk 1831-1921, 6 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Organized into the following subseries: Correspondence, Legal and Financial Documents, Notebooks and Diaries, Notes and Writings, Print Materials, and Visual Materials and Artifacts. Materials relate to the family, their Redcastle estate in County Donegal, relations between the Doherty and Cochrane families, and the naval careers of brothers Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane and Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane. Detailed subseries descriptions follow below.
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1777-1904 and undated, bulk 1831-1904, 2 boxes
    Contains the correspondence of the Cochrane family, primarily correspondence sent to Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane and Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane, but also including a few letters written by them. The majority of the material pertains to their naval careers, but personal and family letters are also included. This subseries also includes four folders of letter drafts by Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane. All correspondence is arranged chronologically by date.
    - Correspondence
      - 1777, 1793, 1820, 1831-1876 (39 folders) (Box 1)
      - 1874-1904 (19 folders) (Box 2)
      - Undated (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Drafts
      - 1876 Mar. 31-June 8 (3 folders) (Box 2)
      - Undated (Box 2)
  - Legal and Financial Documents Subseries, 1825-1921, 2 boxes
    Contains legal papers pertaining to the naval careers of Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane and Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane, including the letter appointing Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane commander in the navy, and several letters of certification; letters patent to Sir Thomas Cochrane, James Parker, Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane, and Walter Burnham, for ship propulsion systems, a method for laying telegraph wire, and a means of heating and evaporating liquids to be used in ships' boilers; court documents from multiple legal cases with which the Cochrane family was involved, including a book and a pamphlet of transcripts of testimony given, as well as a legal brief for the suit brought against Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane by James Moore Doherty over the letting of family land in County Donegal; loose sales slips and receipts; a number of rental and account books for the Doherty and Cochrane family estates, and farm account books for same; a Land Commission notebook of Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane; and legal documents pertaining to land laws and use in Ireland. Loose documents are arranged chronologically by date; logbooks and account books are arranged chronologically by year.
    - Loose items (Box 3)
      - 1825-1888, Legal and financial documents (Box 3)
      - 1906, Printed material pertaining to the relief of land congestion in Ireland (Box 3)
      - Undated, Legal and financial documents (Box 3)
    - Bound volumes
      - 1833-1834, Doherty account book (Box 3)
      - 1844, 1848, Financial notebook (Box 3)
      - 1871, Rental and account book (Box 3)
      - 1872-1873, 1885-1887, 1888-1890, Farm account books (5 volumes) (Box 3)
      - 1889 Mar. 16, Booklet containing "Statements of Fact" by James Harvey (Box 3)
      - 1895-1896, Farm diary (Box 3)
      - 1897-1903, Land Commission notebook of Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane (Box 4)
  - Notebooks and Diaries Subseries, 1847-1904, 1 box
    Folders house navigation logs and personal diaries of Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane. The personal diaries document his health, activities (both business and personal), and diet from day to day. Also included are a surveying notebook and Nova Scotia travel diary of Thomas Cochrane from the 1850s, a Barbados almanac from 1873 (author unidentified), and a scrapbook. Items are arranged chronologically.
    - 1847, 1856, Navigation log books (2 books) (Box 4)
    - 1851 Aug.-Sept., Nova Scotia travel diary of Thomas Cochrane (Box 4)
    - 1854, 1859, 1861, 1864, 1897 and undated, Scrapbook containing 4 letters, 1 diagram of a plough, 1 nautical chart, and 1 concession pamphlet for the Trinidad Lake Asphalt Company (Box 4)
    - Circa 1850s, Surveying notebook of Thomas Cochrane (Box 4)
    - 1869-1870, Sheerness Stockyard logbook (Box 4)
    - 1873, Barbados almanac (Box 4)
    - 1899, 1903-1904, Personal diaries (3 diaries) (Box 4, 5)
    - Undated, Mathematics notebook (Box 5)
  - Notes and Writings Subseries, 1839-1899, 3 folders
    Contains personal and nautical notes (lists of ship complements, written drafts of official documents, blank forms for recording readings, invalid reports and leave application forms, and a meteorological register) by Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane and Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane, as well as results of various experiments conducted by the Cochranes. Since they are mostly for personal or ship use, most of these are unsigned and many are undated. Those that are dated are arranged chronologically by date, while the others remain unsorted.
    - 1839-1865 (Box 5)
    - 1868-1899 (Box 5)
    - Undated (Box 5)
  - Print Materials Subseries, 1847-1911, 1 folder
    Contains a pamphlet in Spanish on the province of Carabaya, Peru from 1847; clippings relating to the Cochrane family, the naval careers of members of the family, issues of naval safety and laws, the proposals for the establishment of canals in the Americas (including the Panama Canal), and the death notices for both Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane and Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane; a printed letter by Santiago González, the President of El Salvador, regarding the fall of Amapala in 1873; a service guide for Lent, 1897 in the parish of Bray; broadsheets relating to the deaths of several members of the Doherty family in a boating accident, and to the Ulster Fisheries and Biology Association; a booklet detailing Lethwaite's system of constructing breakwaters; an undated pamphlet on cargo regulations and customs laws in Lisbon; and various calling cards. Items are arranged chronologically by date.
    - 1847, 1854, 1862, 1873, 1882, 1897-1900, 1906, 1911 and undated (Box 5)
  - Visual Materials and Artifacts Subseries, 1868-1930, 10 folders
    Comprises drawings, charts, maps, and photographs relating to the Cochranes' naval careers and estate in Ireland. Also includes an envelope of fish hooks from Nova Scotia, and a large map of Louise Mines in Pennsylvania. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1875, A sounding chart and drawing of Kilauea's Berth by H.C. Kingsford (Box 5)
    - 1882, Envelope of fish hooks from Nova Scotia (Box 5)
    - Circa 1885, 1889 and undated, Photographs of and around the Redcastle estate (3 items) (Box 5)
    - 1930 July 1, Two photographs of McGladerey's Brickfield in Belfast (Box 5)
    - Undated, Watercolors and drawings from Acapulco Bay and the Galapagos Islands, signed by "Sisson" (Box 5)
    - Undated, Hand-drawn map of an unidentified harbor, signed by Captain Chihochoff of the transport Dwina (Box 5)
    - Undated, Photograph labelled "The Last co. Donegal Grand Jury" (Box 5)
    - Undated, Photograph of the H.M.S. Petrel (Box 5)
- Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane Series, 1811-1957 bulk 1847-1911, 2 boxes
  Contains material relating to the life of Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane and his children, as well as his dealings with the Doherty family in County Donegal. Arranged into the following subseries: Correspondence, Legal and Financial Documents, Notebooks and Diaries, Notes and Writings, Print Materials, and Visual Materials. Subseries descriptions follow below.
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1833-1931 bulk 1847-1910, 5 folders
    Consists of correspondence sent to and from Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane. Correspondents include Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane, Thomas Cochrane, Francis E. Hubbard, and Samuel W. Blackwall. This subseries also contains significant correspondence between Richard Doherty, Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane, and others regarding the Redcastle Estate in County Donegal and proposed plans to build a railway across the land, and some letters sent to Arthur Auckland Leopold Pedro Cochrane by others. Arranged chronologically by date.
    - Correspondence, 1833 July 16-1931 Aug. 31 (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, Undated (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Legal and Financial Documents Subseries, 1823-1950 bulk 1858-1924, 4 folders
    Apart from folders housing the legal and financial papers of Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane and his children, the subseries also contains a packet of letters certifying Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane's naval service, and a folder of marks and report cards for the children of Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1823, 1845-1849, 1858-1868, Legal and financial documents (Box 6)
    - 1847-1850, Certification letters (Box 6)
    - 1856, 1867, 1882, Marks and report cards (Box 6)
    - 1870-1898, Legal and financial documents (Box 6)
    - 1902-1924, 1939, 1950 and undated, Legal and financial documents (Box 6)
  - Notebooks and Diaries Subseries, 1854-1880, 1 box
    Contains notebooks, diaries, pocket almanacs, and letter copybooks of Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1854-1864, Almanacs (9 volumes) (Box 7)
    - 1868-1869, Diaries (2 volumes) (Box 7)
    - 1868, Notebook and Bermuda travel diary (1 volume) (Box 7)
    - 1869-1870, 1878-1880, Letter copybook (1 volume) (Box 7)
    - 1870, Letter copybook (1 volume) (Box 7)
    - Undated, Army signalling scribbling book (1 volume) (Box 7)
    - Undated, Crew list book for H.M.S. Blenheim (1 volume) (Box 7)
  - Notes and Writings Subseries, 1843-1900, 1 folder
    Comprises notes and other miscellaneous writings and sketches by Ernest Grey Lambton Cochrane. Since they are mostly for personal or ship use, most of these are unsigned and many are undated. Those that are dated are arranged chronologically by date, while the others remain unsorted.
    - 1843-1900 and undated (Box 6)
  - Print Materials Subseries, 1811-1957, 1 folder